<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of religious prudence a sermon preach'd before the Queen at White-Hall, on Sunday, Sept. 17, 1693 / by Thomas Mannyngham ...</title>
            <author>Manningham, Thomas, 1651?-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6637</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12636952</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12636952</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64908</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51813)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64908)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 697:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of religious prudence a sermon preach'd before the Queen at White-Hall, on Sunday, Sept. 17, 1693 / by Thomas Mannyngham ...</title>
                  <author>Manningham, Thomas, 1651?-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs VIII, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Prudence --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64908:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64908:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Of Religious Prudence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the QUEEN AT <hi>WHITE-HALL,</hi> On Sunday, <hi>Sept.</hi> 17. 1693.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Thomas Mannyngham, <hi>Rector of St.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew-Holborn, <hi>and Chaplain in Ordinary to Their</hi> MAJESTIES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh by her Majeſty's Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Crooke,</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Barr,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:64908:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64908:2"/>
            <head>Prov. VIII. Verſe 12. former part.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>I Wiſdom dwell with Prudence.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>ALtho' Wiſdom be brought in by <hi>Solomon</hi> in this Chapter, ſpeaking of her ſelf, as a Perſon; and upon that account, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Ancients in their Interpretations, have underſtood it myſtically of the Eternal Son of God, the Wiſdom of the Father, from whom all true Wiſdom is derived; yet according to the common Language, and general deſign of theſe Proverbial Writings, Wiſdom ſtands for <hi>Religion,</hi> and Religion is expreſs'd by the <hi>Fear of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prudence is either Univerſal or Particular: Univerſal Prudence is the ſame with the Doctrine of Morality, the Application of the moſt proper means, <hi>viz.</hi> Vertuous Actions, towards the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring the chief End, the Happineſs of Man: And Particular Prudence is diſtinguiſh'd by the different Objects and Ends about which it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant, and is the proſecution of any lawful De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign by ſuch Methods as ſhall appear to be beſt, upon a due Conſideration of Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>That which is immediately ſignifi'd by the Words of the Text, <hi>I Wiſdom dwell with Prudence,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64908:3"/>is this, That there is an inſeparable Connexion between Religion and Prudence; that one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be without the other; neither Religion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Prudence, nor Prudence without Religion.</p>
            <p>One would think that this were ſo plain a Truth, that it could bear no enlargement, either for the Illuſtrating or the Confirming of it: But he who conſiders what perverſneſs of Opinions obtains among Mankind, ariſing from the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Manners, and the immoderate love of preſent Life; will be ready to acknowledge, that there are thoſe in the World, who frame to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a Notion of Prudence, which has no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon Religion; and practiſe it without any regard to the Laws of Juſtice: And on the other ſide, whoever conſiders what an unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble awe Superſtition imprints on the Minds and Conſciences of ſome, and how often it happens that a Zeal without Knowledge paſſes for the height of Piety; will readily confeſs, that there are many who pretend to be very Devout, but they want that Prudence, which ſhould juſtifie their Actions, and adorn their Religion.</p>
            <p>And now upon this view of things, my Text which aſſerts a neceſſary Connexion between Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Prudence, will bear an enlargement in theſe <hi>Three</hi> reſpects.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64908:3"/>
            <list>
               <item>I. That there is no true Political Prudence, but what is founded upon Religion, or the Fear of God.</item>
               <item>II. That the Pious Man is in the main, the truly Prudent and Judicious Perſon.</item>
               <item>III. I ſhall ſhew, what great uſe there is of a particular Prudence in the Conduct of a Religious Life.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. There is no true Political Prudence, but what is founded upon Religion, or the Fear of God.</p>
            <p>God has deliver'd the World not only to the Enquiries and Diſputations of Men, but in a great meaſure he has given them the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it too; reſerving to himſelf a Power over Nature, and a Prerogative over all humane Counſels and Actions. We may ſtudy and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve thoſe Laws of Motion which are imprinted on the Univerſe, as accurately and as nicely as we can; but we muſt not exclude the Firſt Mover; who gave beginning to, and ſtill ſuſtains thoſe Powers which we call Nature: We may likewiſe carry on our Publick Affairs and Private Buſineſs, by the exacteſt Rules of honeſt Management, and wiſe Diſpatch; but then we muſt aſcribe the ſucceſs of all to the Providence of God, who over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rules things into what Events he pleaſes, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64908:4"/>brings to paſs his own Counſels by humane en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours.</p>
            <p>The firſt Corruption in Natural Philoſophy conſiſted in the pretending to give an account of the World and its Original, without an infinite Underſtanding and Firſt Mover: And the main Corruption of Prudence does conſiſt in attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Government of the World by humane Policy, without a due ſubmiſſion to the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God. But as the moſt ancient and beſt Philoſophers never undertook to explain Nature without having recourſe to an Infinite Spirit and Mind; ſo we find in this Book of <hi>Proverbs,</hi> that the ancient Political Prudence was founded on the Fear of God: For ſo Wiſdom ſpeaks in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Counſel is mine, and ſound wiſdom: I am under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, I have ſtrength. By me Kings reign, and Primes decree juſtice. By me Princes rule, and Nobles, even all the Judges of the earth,</hi> Prov. VIII. 14, 15, 16.</p>
            <p>Becauſe, in the ordinary courſe of things, the general Influence of a Superior Being, is collected only by Reaſon and Inference; and the particular working of Secondary Cauſes is conſpicuous to Sence, and manifeſt to common Experience; it often happens, that the proud Reaſoners, and the ſenſual part of Mankind, either wholly deny a Providence, or attribute very little to its Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendency
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64908:4"/>and Power: But then theſe are the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whoſe Counſels are generally blaſted, and who are often ſcatter'd in their own Imaginations: Tho' they proſper in ſome few Attempts, yet their main Deſign miſcarries; and when the wiſe Ends of Providence are ſeiv'd, their vain Projections are daſh'd in pieces. We indeed are deſirous of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Diſappointments of the Wicked much ſooner than they commonly happen; but we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get how a Providential Diſpenſation uſually takes a large circuit, and is not ſo ſoon finiſh d as our Impatience would have it: In theſe Matters, we are to govern our Perſuaſions by what has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready been done in other Ages, and if any thing appear very Irregular to us at preſent, we may be aſſur'd upon the confidence of former Events, that Divine Wiſdom will bring it into its proper Channel again.</p>
            <p>The Univerſal Hiſtory of the World, and the Particular Hiſtories of Kingdoms, and of ſome more Eminent Families, are full of the Tragical Ends of thoſe proud Politicians, who thought to govern without God, and to be prudent without Religion: Their unjuſt Methods ſucceeded for ſome time, for the Puniſhment of a degenerate People, and then the Executioners themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d the like Chaſtiſement from another ſett of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64908:5"/>proſpering Sinners, who having ſcourg'd their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, fell at laſt under the ſame Indignation which they had meaſur'd to others.</p>
            <p>The horrible Wickedneſs of Mankind ſeems to have made the permiſſion of ſome ſort of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Tyranny, almoſt neceſſary in the World, from the ancient Times of <hi>Nimrod,</hi> through all the Four Great Monarchies: But the exceeding dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy of Chriſtians, ſeems to have given occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the multiplying of that Evil, and for the erecting many Tyrannies in the World at one time: The Antichriſtian Polity, the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and the <hi>French</hi> Ambition, do all contribute to the puniſhing of wicked Chriſtians; for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly 'tis our Impiety that is the principal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why theſe great Tyrannies are permitted in the World: Yet even <hi>Theſe</hi> ſhall have their ſignal Judgments, their Devaſtations, and Decays; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a total Ruine, or a tranſlation from one Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to another, to make it evident, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God is over all, and diſpoſes things for the beſt Advantage of the World; that there may be a Diſpenſation of Temporal Calamities, for thoſe Kingdoms which are otherwiſe incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, who may be ſure of Proſperity when they veturn to their Vertue again.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:64908:5"/>
            <p>Moſt of thoſe Perſons, who make uſe of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt means, to free themſelves from any preſent Diſtreſs, or to advance themſelves to any Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency in the World, beſides the direct Impiety of their Hearts, have uſually ſuch poor and narrow minds, as cannot contemplate the Providence of God with any due extent of Thought; nor conſider things with thoſe Relations, and with thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, in the viewing of which the Excellency of Man above other Creatures does conſiſt, and the proper Wiſdom of his Mind is diſplay'd: And ſhall we allow thoſe to be Prudent, who neither Reaſon nor Conſider, who never weigh the Juſtice and Expediency of an Action, which depends upon Laws and Permiſſions; but run from every thing that diſpleaſes, and ruſh upon every thing that they fancy, without any reſpect to the Obligations of Honeſty and Right? If to avoid what one diſlikes, and to obtain what one deſires, by any means whatever, were all that were requir'd in Prudence, then <hi>common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct</hi> might ſerve the Turn as well as Reaſon; for that ſupplies ſome Creatures with Tricks and Shifts enough to compaſs and effect their little Ends: But a <hi>Natural Sagacity</hi> is not ſufficient for Man, who is accountable for his Actions, who muſt engage on no Deſigns but what are Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64908:6"/>nor purſue them by any means but what are Juſt and Lawful.</p>
            <p>That Wiſdom which degenerates into Craft, is but equivocally call'd Wiſdom, 'tis really Folly, a miſchievous, ſhifting, Artificial Folly; that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceals it ſelf a while, but throws off its diſguiſe at laſt; that looks like wiſe and proſperous Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ſome time, but ends in Ignominious Ruine. The Man of Integrity and Conſcience needs no Arts of Diſſimulation, the more he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, the ſooner is he truſted; and the more he depends on God and his own Sincerity, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſucceeds. Tho' Honeſty and true Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence can never be really ſeparated in the main Actions of Life, yet it is better to live without the <hi>Opinion</hi> of <hi>Prudence,</hi> than without that of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty;</hi> for do but ſeparate the Opinion of <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity</hi> from any one, and then the more Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual and Subtil he is, the more he is ſuſpected and avoided; but Men will put a great Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in him, who has an honeſt Heart and a good Meaning, tho' he has not ſo large a reach of Underſtanding as the other: There is a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Preſage that things will ſucceed well in the Hands of thoſe who are Vertuous, that a Propitiouſneſs will attend them in all their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, that what they want in Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64908:6"/>will be made up by a Felicity of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
            <p>Whereas 'tis generally expected that Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhould befool the greateſt Parts, give a check to the boldeſt Spirits, and blaſt the beſt Deſigns: Wherefore there is no ſurer way to Honour and Eminence, even in wicked Times, than to have a general Reputation of being a Perſon of true Piety and Conſcience: He ſhall have the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the People, and the Love of his Country, when the Man of Impiety and ill Morals, tho' never ſo extraordinary in other Reſpects, ſhall be ſecretly deſpis'd; and the Hypocrite, tho' never ſo cloſe and ſpecious for a while, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, and diſmiſs'd with Confuſion.</p>
            <p>An Uprightneſs of Action, a Conſtancy in Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and unmovable Frame of Mind and Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, of always purſuing what is Juſt and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to the Publick, by right and laudable ways, is that which will make a Man Fortunate, or deſerving to be ſo in the general Eſteem of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; 'twill make him truly Valuable, even with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Riches or Titles; twill make him truly Great and Reverenc'd, and fit for the higheſt Truſt, tho' he be not imploy'd: But, for the moſt part, 'tis the ready and direct Road to all the deſirable things of this Life; Juſtice being
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64908:7"/>the ſureſt Path to Greatneſs, honeſt Dealing the moſt provable way of growing Rich; and thoſe being uſually the moſt reſpected, and the moſt belov'd, who walk through this World, and its ſeveral Stages of Duty, in the plain Garb of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity and Truth.</p>
            <p>To ſeparate Political Prudence from Religion, is not only Impiety, but the extremity of Folly too: For, is Man able to over-rule the various Contingencies of this Life? Can he fix the Thoughts? Can he determine and point the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of others to his particular Deſigns? And yet a Concurrence of theſe is requir'd to every Event; and Mankind in all Ages were ſo ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of this, that in their more conſiderable Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, they always made an eſpecial Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to ſome Superior Power: Liberty of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and Deſign, with the Care of Preparations, is all that Man can boaſt of; but the Succeſs of Actions depends on Circumſtances without his reach: Therefore Men were ſtill deſirous of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what was the <hi>Divine Will,</hi> as to thoſe Affairs in which they were ready to engage. Many of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Nations attempted to read the <hi>Will</hi> of their Gods in the Stars and Conſtellations; the <hi>Grecians</hi> conſulted their famous Oracles, and the <hi>Romans</hi> depended much upon their Auguries;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64908:7"/>but the Holy Scriptures are our ſtanding Oracle, where God has deliver'd his Immutable Will, <hi>that he will deſtroy the wiſdom of the World, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the proud in the imagination of their Hearts;</hi> and <hi>though a ſinner do evil an hundred times, and his days he prolonged,</hi> yet <hi>Solomon</hi> aſſures us as of the Decree of God, <hi>that it ſhall be well with them that fear the Lord,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall endeavour to ſhew, that the Pious Perſon in the main is the truly Judicious.</p>
            <p>If we would ſpeak according to the Accuracy of Moral Writers, Wiſdom is the Knowledge of things Great, Admirable, and Divine, whereby the Mind is rais'd and enlarg'd into delightful Contemplations; and Prudence is a right Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Judgment, or the Skill of judging what we are to do, and what not, and of diſtinguiſhing between Good and Evil, and the degrees of each: And tho' Prudence in the common ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of the World, paſſes now for any Cunning Contrivance, for any dextrous Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an Affair, whatever means are us'd; yet the ancient Moraliſts never allow'd a wicked Man to be call<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d Prudent: They readily grant, that ſuch an one may have a ſubtilty of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and an acuteneſs in ſpeculative Studies, and that he may be well skill'd in all the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64908:8"/>of Craft; but they unanimouſly declare, that a wicked Life corrupts the very Principles of true Prudence, and right Reaſon; which cannot dwell with Paſſions, and irregular Deſires.</p>
            <p>Prudence is that Vertue or Power of the Soul, whereby the Mind deliberates rightly, and finds out what is beſt to be done, when all things are conſider'd; or, it helps us to diſcover what are the beſt Means for obtaining a Good End: Now 'tis Religion that qualifies the Mind to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider Practical Matters in their true Nature and Conſequences; that purifies the Intention, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects the Inclinations, moderates the Affections, and makes our Deliberations calm and wiſe: 'Tis the Fear of God that ſets Bounds to Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that ſhews how far we are to act in any Undertaking, and where we are to reſign things up to a higher Conduct: 'Tis Temperance that gives us an Intellectual Vigor, that makes us Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of our Reaſon, that preſents a clear Proſpect to the Eyes of Wiſdom, void of all the Miſts and Colours of Fancy; and frees our Thoughts from the Contagion of our Temper: 'Tis the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of another Life, that cools our Deſires after this; and makes us content to let the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of this; World alone, if they cannot be acquir'd without Sin, which is the certain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64908:8"/>of our beſt and higheſt Intereſts: Theſe and ſuch-like Vertues are the Pre-requiſites, or the Ingredients of all true Prudence; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis the <hi>Pious</hi> Man, that in the main is the truly <hi>Judicious</hi> Perſon.</p>
            <p>But then, does not this ſound like an uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Aſſertion? And is it not often made an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Objection, that ſuch an One is very Good and Vertuous, but he is very Imprudent, and wants a Knowledge of Men and Buſineſs? But yet, if Religion be the higheſt Prudence, as has been already prov'd, then this Aſſertion muſt ſtill hold, That the truly Pious Man in the main is, the truly Judicious Perſon; and the miſtake of the World muſt lie in this; That either their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent Perſon is not truly Pious, but rather En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſtick, or Superſtitious, or intemperately Zealous, or the like; or, elſe they vainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that there is no true Prudence, but that which tends to make Men Rich and Great in this World, by any Means, and by any Arts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever: Now this is ſo far from being any part of Prudence, that 'tis the very Principle which the Scriptures brand as Folly in the higheſt degree; ſuch Folly, as does not only, ſignifie the Weakneſs of the Judgment, but the Malignity of the Will; which is not bare Imprudence, but groſs Sin and Vice.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64908:9"/>
            <p>There is indeed a very low ſort of Prudence, which does conſiſt in being mighty ſedulous and diligent in getting of Wealth, and raiſing a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, by ſuch ways as are not unjuſt in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of humane Laws, tho' not ſo becoming a Chriſtian, who is to make the Concerns of another World his principal Care and Buſineſs: But why ſhould the heaping up of Riches be look'd upon as the main Evidence and mark of Mens Prudence? Surely there is much more Diſcretion requir'd in uſing of them temperately, and diſpoſing of them wiſely to Charitable uſes; and in making them a foundation of preſent Comfort, and future Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: Why is not the diſcreet Management of a narrow Fortune, as clear a ſign of Prudence, as the getting a large and ample one? And why is not a good Reputation an excellent Purchaſe, as well as a good Eſtate? The Prudence of this World is made a Pattern in the Goſpel for Chriſtians to imitate in their purſuit after the Happineſs of the next, but as to its own Nature it is always rejected and condemn'd: We may borrow ſomething of its Caution and Warineſs in times of Perſecution and Danger, but never make uſe of its baſe Deſigns, or of its unjuſt and unworthy Methods.</p>
            <p>The beſt way of coming to Riches, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and of obtaining the Advantages of this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64908:9"/>Life, is the being very diligent in procuring the Favour of Him who is the giver of every good and perfect Gift: And then the Prudence which concerns us in this caſe, is a faithful and diligent acting in that Station that is appointed us, with a due Subordination to God and his Laws; the keeping up a continual ſucceſſion of Induſtry and Prayer, which will be ſure to carry us diſcreetly through all the neceſſary Buſineſs of Life; and either make us ſucceſsful in what we undertake, or ſupport us under diſappointments; affording us this conſtant ſatisfaction, that tho' our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Deſigns do not always proſper, yet our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Deſires are always accompliſh'd in the good Providence of God.</p>
            <p>'Tis a very imperfect Notion of Prudence, to think that it conſiſts in an exact Knowledge of the World, or in getting a large ſhare and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it: I ſhould rather define it, a diſcreet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of this World, and an earneſt ſeeking after ſuch good things as are real and laſting, as are perfective of our Nature, and more within our Power, than thoſe, which we call the Goods of Fortune, are. An exact Knowledge in Buſineſs, and a long Experience in the Affairs of humane Life, contribute much to true Prudence, when there is a Religious Principle at the bottom, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64908:10"/>a ſober and temperate Mind to make a good uſe of that Knowledge; but otherwiſe it only ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies Men with a more pernicious Craft, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables them to lay their Frauds the deeper. That part of Prudence which ſerves to keep a Man from being cheated by others, may be beſt learn'd by obſerving the general Falſeneſs of the World; but that which will preſerve him from being chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by himſelf, by his own vain Reaſonings, and fooliſh Paſſions; is the looking into his own Heart, and taking a full view of the deceitfulneſs of that little World; it is the guarding himſelf from the Illuſions of his ſenſual Nature, and the purging his Soul from thoſe defilements, which put falſe Colours upon the Mind, that it cannot diſcern its trueſt Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Let the Underſtanding be clear, the Reaſon ſober, the Will orderly, and the Paſſions govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; and then what will there be wanting to make that Man Prudent? Nothing ſurely, beſides a thorough Acquaintance with, and an actual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the particular Buſineſs which ſhall at any time be laid before him.</p>
            <p>They who are ſubject to an exceſſive heat and impetuouſneſs of Temper, or are much given to contemplative and abſtracted Studies, are not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally thought very proper to be imploy'd in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64908:10"/>Publick Affairs, tho' they be Perſons of a good Life and Meaning: But then, let not Religion be blam'd for thoſe Defects which are no ways owing to Religion, or which ariſe from the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation of ſome <hi>Niceneſſes,</hi> which Religion does not require: It muſt be confeſs'd, that much Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement, and deep Devotion, will bring ſome good Men to ſuch an exceeding tenderneſs of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in all their <hi>Civil</hi> as well as Religious Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; as Men who are more exercis'd in the World, and more inur'd to Publick Affairs, will be apt to Cenſure as an imprudent, and unneceſſary ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulouſneſs of Mind: And on the other ſide, it muſt be acknowledg'd, That a Nation may come to be ſo generally corrupted, and ſo divided by Intereſts and Parties, that a Man ſhall be hard put to it, to keep his Integrity, and his Publick Station together: And when things ſhall at any time come to this deſperate State, it will be impoſſible for the Man of Conſcience, and the Man of Politicks, to agree in their Notion of Prudence.</p>
            <p>It is certain, That we are firſt to ſerve God, to ſeek his Kingdom and Righteouſneſs; and then to ſecure our Juſt Intereſts in this World: But when our Civil Intereſts about which we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, are ſuch, as immediately reſpect the Peace and Quiet of Government, and are ſo important
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64908:11"/>a Care, that the very exerciſe and eſtabliſhment of our Religion depends upon it, then Prudence may be allow'd to act in a greater Latitude, and ſtill be within the bounds of Juſtice; and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Welfare of a Nation will require ſome larger meaſures of Compliance in extraordinary Caſes, which yet ſhall be no ways injurious to Religion and a good Conſcience. A firmneſs of Soul, a ſolidity of Judgment, and a fix'd Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Vertue, are rare and Noble Qualities; but a very timerous and ſcrupulous Mind is an Imperfection in any one, but chiefly in ſuch as ſuſtain a Publick Character, and are oblig'd to act for the greateſt Good and Welfare of <hi>others;</hi> 'tis an Infirmity that breeds Delays, that loſes the opportunity of Action, that makes Men inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with their own Counſels, dubious and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in all their Undertakings; and Inconſtancy does ſometimes as much miſchief to the Publick, as Ignorance and Malice; it likewiſe tempts many to ſpeak reproachful things of Probity and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion it ſelf, and to call in queſtion the Prudence of thoſe, whoſe private Vertues are moſt deſervedly in great eſteem. And ſo I come to the</p>
            <p n="3">III. Thing propos'd, <hi>viz.</hi> To ſpeak ſomething concerning that Particular Prudence which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd in the Conduct of a Religious Life.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:64908:11"/>
            <p>No Pious Perſon can be ſuppos'd to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that which we call Moral Prudence, for that belongs to the Eſſence of Vertue, and runs through every Duty; but, beſides this, there are other things requir'd to make a Man perfect and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in Prudence; ſuch as good Natural Parts, liberal Education, much Experience, wiſe Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and an application to thoſe of greater Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity than our ſelves: Some of which, are matter of Advice and Counſel, ſuch as the converſing with Men of great Knowledge, and excellent Temper; and the applying our ſelves to thoſe who are eminent for Wiſdom and Vertue. Others are occaſional Advantages, or a Providential Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity; ſuch as good Natural Parts, and liberal Education, and much Experience in the World.</p>
            <p>Now as it is not indiſpenſably neceſſary for every one to be Vertuous in the very ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and degree; much leſs is it abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd, that every Religious Perſon ſhould be Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to juſt ſuch an extent: That which is our direct Duty in reſpect to this and all other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Attainments, is to uſe our beſt Endeavours to acquire them; and the higher we advance in the Rational and Spiritual Nature, the more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and ſecure we are.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:64908:12"/>
            <p>There may be much Imprudency mingled with an honeſt Simplicity of Mind, with an humble Piety, and an hearty Deſire of doing good; but then, that Imprudency is in ſmall matters, and not in ſuch things as belong to the ſubſtance of Duty; for I cannot conceive how a truly Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſon can be to ſeek in any of the real Parts and Inſtances of Vertue; in ſome particular De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies of it he may: If he has not the Natural Bleſſing of a clear Underſtanding, yet if he has the Humility of a good Chriſtian, that will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect him in <hi>many</hi> Caſes to make his application to thoſe, who have that larger meaſure of Prudence which he wants: And if this were duly practis'd, what a multitude of Irregularities in Religion might be prevented, which take their riſe from an Imprudent Zeal? A Pious Temper is the firſt thing we are to labour after, and a Prudent Mind is the next; by the firſt we are ſincerely diſpos'd to do all the Good we can; and by the other we are enabled to judge when, and where, and by what means that Good is to be done; how every Duty may be beſt perform'd, how ſeaſonably, and in its time, and how conſiſtent with other Obligations which muſt not be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:64908:12"/>
            <p>When ſenſual and ſelfiſh Principles are laid aſide, the Mind purifi'd, the Paſſions in ſubjection, and the Glory of God unfeignedly deſign'd in all our Actions; where there is no ſpiritual Pride, no vain affectation of ſeeming more than ordinary ſcrupulous even about indifferent Matters; but an humble, modeſt, and careful progreſs in Duty; there Religious Prudence is never wanting: which is a ſagacity of diſcerning not only the great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of Good and Evil, but the various de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Goodneſs, and the peculiar ſeaſons of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Actions: For there is a <hi>particular Prudence</hi> which ought to accompany every Duty, which gives it a proper grace and beauty, makes it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo commendable and lovely in the Eyes of all who behold it, that they who will not practiſe it, know not how to condemn it. Sermons, and Pious Conferences; Caſes of Conſcience, and Books of Spiritual Wiſdom, do all contribute to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Improving of People in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Religious Prudence; which being ſo large and comprehenſive a ſubject, I ſhall not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to diſcourſe it fully at the latter end of a Sermon, but only lay down <hi>Three</hi> or <hi>Four</hi> Rules for the more prudent Conduct of a Religious Life.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Rule is this: Not to engage in things which are above our Sphere. Moſt People
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64908:13"/>have a ſtrange affectation of being Publick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before they are call'd to it; they will not reſt contented with a private and modeſt Piety, but love to do ſomething that is extraordinary, as they think, that they may be obſerv'd and talk'd of: Tho' Providence has plac'd them in that ſtate, wherein their Eminency is to be ſhewn by their Obedience, yet they are impatient to cenſure things which are not of their Level, and were never intended for their Examination: They think they do not anſwer the ſtrong Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe of their Religion, unleſs they oppoſe their Zeal without Knowledge againſt ſuch Matters as are wholly Prudential. You are willing to do Good, but muſt you go out of your Bounds to do it? You would give faithful Counſel and Advice, but why muſt it be immediately directed to your Governors? Are not the Miſcarriages of your own Family, or of your Neighbourhood, a more proper Subject for your Animadverſions? Or, are you ſure, that your own Innocence will give you the Authority? Or, that your own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects will allow you the leiſure of Correcting others? You are deſirous of bettering many things which you think amiſs; but muſt you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move things, which have been found Good up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on long trial, to make way for your Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64908:13"/>You would uphold the tottering Ark, but muſt you thruſt out a prophane Hand to ſupport it? You would have more Purity in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, but muſt you make a Schiſm to obtain it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If Men would be Prudently Religious, they muſt not preſently catch at Perfection, and the higheſt Inſtances of Piety. There is an order of Duties, and a gradual advancement in Religion: They who affect Sublimities, before they are eſtabliſh'd in Humility, will never come to any ſtrength and conſiſtency in Vertue; and will bring but little Honour to the Profeſſion of the Goſpel. What mad work do thoſe poor Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſts make in Religion, who are altogether for the Raptures of Divine Love and Contemplation, before they have mortifi d their Affections and Luſts; who pretend to the greateſt Perfection, when they want the firſt Rudiments of Moral Vertue; and think themſelves highly advanc'd in Spiritual Wiſdom, when they are not ſo much as under the Conduct of common Prudence?</p>
            <p n="3">3. If we would be Prudently Religious, we muſt never engage too vehemently in things of an indifferent Nature. There are ſubſtantial Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties enough to take up all the fervour and viva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of our Zeal, without waſting its force in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64908:14"/>things of a low concern: Humility, Meekneſs, Self-denial, and Prayer, are Duties for all to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, and require our utmoſt application and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor; but thoſe things which are only contingent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Good, and have no real excellency in their own Natures, require but a moderate regard: And 'tis the chief act and imployment of Prudence, to judge rightly of the different value of things, and to proportion our concern to the degrees of Goodneſs, and the meaſures of Expediency.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let us take care that we do not ſpoil a good conſtitution of Soul, by any ſuperſtitious Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, or unneceſſary ſcruples of Conſcience. When we plainly perceive that we are ſincerely Religious, and that we have a clear Integrity of Heart; let us not cloud it by melancholly Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: When our Conſcience is right and ſound, let us not phyſick it too much, by needleſs and perplexing Doubts and Queſtions, leſt we make it too weak and timorous, and unſerviceable for thoſe noble and rational Ends for which it was deſign'd.</p>
            <p>All Imprudencies in Religion are not Sins, but they are Infirmities; they take off the Luſtre of Vertuous Actions, and ſo diminiſh the Glory of Religion; they make People in many reſpects, uncomfortable to themſelves, and unprofitable to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64908:14"/>others; and next to the Purity of the Heart, there is nothing that can be compar'd to the Prudence of the Mind; which I am perſuaded many may obtain, by half that Pains which they take to be Rich and Wealthy. And is it not a plain argument of an exceeding degeneracy of Manners, when that viler ſort of worldly Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, of which the duller part of Mankind are moſt capable, ſhall be generally preferr'd, before that excellent Prudence of which I have now diſcours'd? By which the Throne is eſtabliſh'd and on the account of which, they who ſtand about it, ſhine with true and ſolid Honours: Which is the beſt Ornament of all our Religious Actions, and the trueſt Splendor of Humane Life.</p>
            <p>To conclude; when Men have wearied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in crooked ways, they will acknowledge, That tho' Irreligion gives a larger ſcope of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, yet Piety keeps them in the right, the ſafe, and pleaſant Path; when they have fully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d themſelves with the ſtudies of Hiſtory, Policy, Laws, of the various Humours of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and the moſt refined Reaſons of State; they will find at laſt that the Chriſtian Vertues are the only Arts of Prudence: That Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, Conſtancy, and Fidelity, with the the fear of God, will make them eſteem'd in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64908:15"/>all Governments; give them a Height and Magnanimity of Wiſdom ſuperiour to all the baſe deſigns of private Intereſt, popular Faction, and a falſe Greatneſs: They will find, that 'tis Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which perfects the political Man, which gives a due largeneſs to his Underſtanding, juſtice to his Deſigns, calmneſs to his Counſels, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Temper under all Events, and a Vertuous Conſtancy under all the Reproaches and Violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Wicked and unruly; which generally brings him to great Honours in this Life, but will infallibly Crown his Wiſdom with Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Glory in the World to come.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:64908:15"/>
            <head>Books lately printed for <hi>William Crooke,</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Barr.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AN Inſtitution of General Hiſtory: Or, the Hiſtory of the World: Being a compleat Body thereof, from the beginning of the World, to the Year after <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror came into <hi>England.</hi> By Dr. <hi>W. Howell,</hi> late Chancellor of <hi>Lincoln.</hi> In Fol. In three Volumes.</p>
            <p>Nine Sermons on Publick Occaſions. By Dr. <hi>Tho. Mannyngham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three Sermons on Publick Occaſions. By Dr. <hi>Haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two Sermons on Publick Occaſions. By Dr. <hi>Pelling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two Sermons, by Mr. <hi>Lightonhouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Bynn</hi>'s Sermon, on <hi>Jan.</hi> 30, 1692/3. before the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Budgel</hi>'s Sermon about Prayer.</p>
            <p>Two Sermons of Mr. <hi>Ellesby</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian's Manual. In two Parts. 1. The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techumen: Or, an Account given by the Young Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Knowledge in Religion, before his Admiſſion to the Lord's Supper, as a Ground-work for his right underſtanding of the Sacrament. 2. An Introduction to the Sacrament: Or, a ſhort, ſafe, and plain Way to the Communion-Table; being an Inſtruction for the worthy Receiving the Lord's Supper. To which is added, The Communicant's Aſſiſtant; being Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to that purpoſe; fitted to be uſed before, at, and after the Receiving of the Bleſſed Sacrament. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected for, and familiarly addreſſed to every particular Communicant. By <hi>L. Addiſon,</hi> D.D. Dean of <hi>Litch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</hi> The fourth Edition. Price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64908:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Three Practical Diſcourſes. 1. Upon the Bleſſed Sacrament of the Lord's Supper. 2. Upon Prayer. 3. Upon Charity in its ſeveral Branches, and of the Reaſonableneſs and uſeful Nature of this great Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Vertue. By <hi>E. Pelling,</hi> D.D. Each ſold ſingle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cicero</hi>'s <hi>Laelius.</hi> A Diſcourſe of Friendſhip. Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Paſtoral Dialogue concerning Friendſhip and Love.</p>
            <p>The Caſe of Reſiſtance of the Supreme Powers ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and reſolved, according to the Doctrine of the Holy Scriptures. By <hi>William Sherlock,</hi> D.D. Dean of <hi>Paul's,</hi> and Maſter of the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tracts of Mr. <hi>Thomas Hobbes</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury:</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, 1. <hi>Behemoth,</hi> the Hiſtory of the Cauſes of the Civil Wars of <hi>England,</hi> from 1640 to 1660, printed from the Author's own Copy. Never printed before but with a thouſand faults. 2. An Anſwer to Arch-Biſhop <hi>Bramhall</hi>'s Book, called, <hi>Catching of the Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</hi> 3. An Hiſtorical Narration of Herefie, and the Puniſhment thereof. 4. Philoſophical Problems, dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the King in 1662. But never printed before.</p>
            <p>The Primitive Inſtitution: Or, a Seaſonable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Catechiſing: Wherein is ſhewn the Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Benefits, and Neceſſity thereof. Together with its Suitableneſs to heal the preſent Diſtempers of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church. The Second Edition. By <hi>Lancelot Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſon,</hi> D.D. Dean of <hi>Litchfield.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
